[{"question":"<p><strong>In order to remove the error of parallax when taking measurements with a metre rule, the eyes should be focused<\/strong><\/p>","options":["slantingly towards the left of the markings","slantingly towards the right of the markings","vertically downwards on the markings","vertically upwards on the markings"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A load is pulled at a uniform speed along a horizontal floor by a rope at 45<sup>o<\/sup> to the floor. If the force in the rope is 1500N, what is the frictional force on the load?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1524N","1350N","1260N","1061N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A rocket is fired from the earth's surface to a distant planet. By Newton's law of universal gravitation, the force F will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["increase as r reduces","increases as G varies","remains constant","increases as r increases"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a freely suspended object is pulled to one side and released, it oscillates about the point of suspension because the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acceleration is directly proportional to the displacement","motion is directly away from equilibrium point","acceleration is directly proportion to the square of the displacement","velocity is minimum at the equilibrium point"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A block and tackle is used to raise a load of 250N through a vertical distance of 30m. What is the efficiency of the system if the work done against is 1500J?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["62.55%","73.3%","8.33%","94.3%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a load of 1 kg stretches a cord 1.2 cm, what is the force constant of the cord?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["866Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","833Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","769Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","667Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The pressure at any point in a liquid at rest depends only on the <\/strong><\/p>","options":["depth and the density","mass and the volume","quantity and the surface area","surface area and the viscosity"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A balloon whose volume is 300m<sup>3<\/sup> is filled with hydrogen. If the density of air is 1.3kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>, find the upthrust on the balloon<\/strong><\/p>","options":["3000N","3800N","3900N","4200N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Clinical thermometers are examples of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pressure gas thermometer","resistance thermometer","alcohol thermometer","mercury-in-glass thermometer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Two metals P and Q are heated throught the same temperature difference. If the ratio of the linear expansivities of P to Q is 2:3 and the ratio of their length if 3:4 respectively, the ratio of the increase in lengths of P to Q is <\/strong><\/p>","options":["1:2","2:1","8:9","9:8"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A body of weight WN rests on a smooth plane inclined at an angle \u03f4<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal. The component of the weight down the slope is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Wsin\u03f4","Wcos\u03f4","Wtan\u03f4","-Wsec\u03f4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A body of mass 100g moves with a velocity of 10.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup> and collides with wall after the collision the body moves with a velocity of 2.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in the opposite direction. The change in momentum is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["8.0Ns","1.2Ns","12.0Ns","1.80Ns"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A 12v battery supplying a current of 20A was used to melt 1.5kg of ice at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the time required if the latent heat of fusion of ice is 336x10<sup>3<\/sup>J\/kg<\/strong><\/p>","options":["35.0min","3.5min","76min","21.0min"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The light from the sun reaches the earth mainly by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["convection","conduction","radiation","reflection"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>One valid assumption of kinetic theory of gases is that:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the molecules are in random motion and the number of collisions is constant","the number of molecules increases with the pressure","the molecules of the gas are all identical and are very small in size","the number of molecules increases with temperature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>An astronomical telescope is said to be in normal adjustment when the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["eye is accomodated","focal length of objective lens is longer than that of the eye piece","final image is at the near point of the eye","final image is at infinity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Dispersion of light by a glass prism is due to the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["different hidden colours of the glass","different speeds of the various colours in glass","defects in the glass","high density of glass"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A battery of internal resistance of 2&amp;#8486; has a voltage of 4.0V when supplying a current of 2.0A. Calculate the terminal voltage if it now supplies a current of 3.0A<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.0V","6.0V","1.5V","12.0V"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The purpose of a dielectric material in a parallel plate capacitor is to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["increase its capacitance","decrease its capacitance","insulate the plates from each other","increase the magnetic field between them"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The name of an atom is associated with its atomic number Z, mass number A and neutron number N. Therefore:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A=Z+N","Z=A+N","N=A+Z","A=N-Z"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A nuclear reaction initiated by adding neutron is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["nuclear fission","nuclear fusion","nuclear enrichment","radioactivity"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A hydrometer is an instrument used for measuring the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["depth of water in a vessel","relative density of a liquid by method of floatation","relative density of a liquid by finding the apparent loss in weight","relative humidity of the atmosphere"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A bead travelling on a straight wire is brought to rest at 0.2m by friction. If the mass of the bead is 0.01kg and the coefficient of friction between the bead and the wire is 0.1, determine the work done by friction from a height of 10m on top of a platform 0.8m above the ground. Its velocity on reaching the platform is&nbsp;(g=9.8ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2x10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","2x10<sup>-3<\/sup>J","0.2x10<sup>1<\/sup>J","0.2x10<sup>2<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mass of gas 7<sup>o<\/sup>C and 70cm of mercury has a volume of 1200cm<sup>3<\/sup>, determine its volume at 27<sup>o<\/sup>C and a pressure at 75cm of mercury<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1200cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1378cm<sup>3<\/sup>","4320cm<sup>3<\/sup>","4629cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A motor tyre is inflated to pressure of 2.0 x 10N\/m<sup>2<\/sup> when the temperature of air is 27<sup>o<\/sup>C what will be the pressure at 87<sup>o<\/sup>C assuming the volume does not change?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.6x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.4x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.2x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","1.3x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A beam of light is incident from air to water at an angle of 30. Find the angle of fraction if the refractive index of water is 4\/3<\/strong><\/p>","options":["15<sup>o<\/sup>","18<sup>o<\/sup>","22<sup>o<\/sup>","240<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Find the frequencies of the first three harmonics of a Piano string of length 5cm, if the velocity of the waves in the string is 120m\/s<\/strong><\/p>","options":["12000HZ, 2400HZ, 3600HZ","1800HZ, 3600HZ, 5400HZ","800HZ, 1600HZ, 2400HZ","3600HZ, 1800HZ, 900HZ"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The resistance of a piece of wire of length 20cm and cross-sectional area 8x10<sup>6<\/sup>m<sup>2<\/sup> and respectively 4x10<sup>7<\/sup>&amp;#8486;m is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1x10<sup>-14<\/sup>&#8486;","10.0&#8486;","400.0&#8486;","1.6x10<sup>-13<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>An electric device is rated 2000W, 250V. The correct fuse railing of the device is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["8A","9A","7A","6A"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Determine the inductive reactance when a 30.0mH inductor with negligible resistance is connected to a 1.3KHz oscillator<\/strong><\/p>","options":["39.0&#8486;","122.5&#8486;","245.0&#8486;","39K&#8486;"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The half life a radioactive element is 9days. What fraction of atoms has decayed in 50days?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1\/16","1\/4","1\/2","15\/16"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The graphite rods surrounding the uranium fuel rods in a nuclear reactor are used to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["absorb the neutrons and hence halts the nuclear process","create the neutrons and hence slows down the nuclear process","slow down the neutrons and hence slow down the nuclear process","speed up the neutrons and hence speed up the nuclear process"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The extension of a spring when 5g weight was hung from it was 0.56cm. If Hooke's law is obeyed, what is the extension caused by a load of 20g weight?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.06m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","0.26m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","3.40m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","12.00m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A car of mass 1500kg goes round a circular curve of radius 50m at a speed of 40m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>. The magnitude of centripetal force on the car is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1.2x10<sup>2<\/sup>N","1.2x10<sup>3<\/sup>N","4.8x10<sup>2<\/sup>N","4.8x10<sup>4<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The efficiency of a machine is always less than 100% because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["work output is always greater than work input","load lifted is always greater than the applied effort","effort applied is always greater than mechanical advantage","velocity ratio is always greater than the mechanical advantage"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these statements is not true? Thermostats are used to control the temperature of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pressure cookers","laundry irons","hot water storage tanks","aquaria for tropical fish"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A given mass of an ideal gas occupies a volume V at a temperature T and under a pressure P. If the pressure is increased to 2P and the temperature reduced to 0.5T, then the percentage change in volume of the gas is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["25%","75%","300%","1%"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The thermometric property of a constant volume thermometer is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["change in pressure","change in length","differential expansion","change in volume"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The combination of sound waves with different frequencies is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["interference","diffraction","superposition","resonance"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following characteristics of a wave is used in the measurement of the depth of the sea?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["refraction","reflection","diffraction","interference"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following eye defects can be corrected using a cylindrical lens?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["astigmatism","presbyopia","chromatic aberration","myopia"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The resistance of a wire depends on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the length of the wire","the arc of the wire","the temperature of the wire","all of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A dynamo primarily converts<\/strong><\/p>","options":["mechanical energy into electrical energy","electrical energy into kinetic energy","potential energy into kinetic energy","kinetic energy into potential energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following may be found in light nuclei?<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>i. B-particles<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>ii. Protons<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>iii. Neutrons<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>iv. A-particles<\/strong><\/p>","options":["i and ii only","i and iii only","i and iv only","ii and iii only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between X-rays and&nbsp;<\/strong><b>\u03b3-<\/b><strong>rays is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["X-rays arise from energy changes and are due to electrons while \u03b3-rays come from the nucleus","X-rays are electromagnetic radiations while \u03b3-rays are not","X-rays have higher frequencies than \u03b3-rays","X-rays are more penetrating than \u03b3-rays"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>When an atom loses or gains a charge, it becomes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["an electron","an ion","a neutron","a proton"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The extension in spring 5g weight hung from it was 0.56cm. If Hooke's law is obeyed, what is the extension caused by a load of 20g weight?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1.12cm","2.14cm","2.52cm","2.24cm"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The distance traveled by a particle starting from rest is plotted against the square of the time elapsed from the commencement of motion. The resulting graph is a measure of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["initial displacement","initial velocity","acceleration","average velocity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A 90cm uniform lever has a load of 30N suspended at 15cm from one of it's end.&nbsp; If the fulcrum is at the center of gravity, the force that must be applied at it's end to keep it in horizontal equilibrium is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["15N","20N","30N","60N"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Two points on a velocity time graph have coordinates (5s,10m\/s) and (20s, 20m\/s). Calculate the mean acceleration between the two points<\/strong><\/p>\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["2.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","5.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","1.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","0.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements are correct?<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>I. Land and sea breezes are natural convection<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>II. The vacuum in a thermos flask prevents heat loss due to convection only<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>III. Convection may occur in liquids or gases but not in solids<\/strong><\/p>","options":["I and II only","II and III only","I and III only","I, II and III only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The property of the eye known as its power accommodation is controlled by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pupil","virtreous humour","iris","cilliary muscles"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Under constant tension and constant mass per unit length, the note produced by a plucked string is 500Hz when the length of the string is 0.9m. At what length is the frequency 150Hz<\/strong><\/p>","options":["3m","0.27m","8.33m","6740m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>An object is placed in front of two plane mirrors inclined at an angle&nbsp;<\/strong><b>\u0472<\/b><strong><sup>o<\/sup>. If the total number of images formed is 7, find the value of&nbsp;<\/strong><span style=\"font-size: 0.875rem; font-weight: bolder;\">\u0472<\/span><span style=\"font-size: 0.875rem; font-weight: bolder;\"><sup style=\"font-size: 10.5px;\">o<\/sup>.<\/span><\/p>","options":["30<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","51<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The north pole of a magnet can never be separated from the South pole because of a property known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["magnetic dipole","magnetic moment","magnetic monopole","magnetic quadru pole"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The terminal voltage of a battery is 4.0V when supplying a current 2.0A and 2.0V when supplying a current of 3.0A. The internal resistance of the battery is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.5","1.0","2.0","4.0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary aim in high tension transmission is to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["minimize electrical energy losses due to heat production","increase the rate of energy transfer by using high voltage","increase the current in the wires","generate electrical current and low voltage"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a set of vectors?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["force, mass and momentum","acceleration, velocity and momemtum","mass, weight and density","mass, volume and density"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A catapult used to hold a stone of mass 500g is extended by 20cm with an applied force F. If the stone leaves with an applied force of 40ms<sup>-1<\/sup> the value of F is?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["40 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>N","4.0 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","4.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A parachute attain a terminal velocity when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["its density is equal to the density of air","the viscous force of the air and the upthrust completely counteract its weight","it expands as a result of reduced external pressure","the viscous force of the air is equal to the sum of the weight and upthrust"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>An electrical heater is used to melt a block of ice, mass 1.5g. If the heater is powered by a 12v battery and current of 20A flows through the coil, calculate the time taken to melt the block of ice at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C (specific latent heat of fusion of ice = 336x10<sup>3<\/sup>JKg<sup>-1<\/sup>)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["76.0mins","35.0mins","21.0mins","2.9mins"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>200g of water at 90<sup>o<\/sup>C is mixed with 100g of water at 30<sup>o<\/sup>C. What is the final temperature?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["20<sup>o<\/sup>","70<sup>o<\/sup>","50<sup>o<\/sup>","10<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The equation&nbsp;<\/strong><b>P<sup style=\"\">x<\/sup>V<sup style=\"\">y<\/sup>T<sup style=\"\">z<\/sup>&nbsp;<\/b><strong>&nbsp;= constant is Charles law when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["x=1, y=1, z=1","x=0, y=1, z=-1","x=1, y=0, z=1","x=0, y=1, z=0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>For a short sighted person, light rays from a point on a very distant object is focused&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["in front of the retina","behind the retina","behind the retina by a diverging lens","in front of the retina, a distance 2F from the lens"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Dispersion of light by a glass prism is due to the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["different hidden colours of the glass","different speeds of various colours in glass","defects in the glass","high density in glass"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>To produce an enlargement and erect image with a concave mirror, the object must be positioned<\/strong><\/p>","options":["between the principal focus and the center curvature","at the principal focus","between the principal focus and the pole","beyond the center of curvature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>To convert an ac dynamo into a dc dynamo, the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["number of turns of the coil is increased","slipt rings are replaced with a split ring commutator","the coil is reduced","split ring commutator is replaced with slip rings"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In an a.c circuit, that contains only a capacitor, the voltage&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["lags behind the current by 90<sup>o<\/sup>","loads the current by W","lags behind the current by 180<sup>o<\/sup>","leads the current by 180<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The purpose of the dielectric material in a parallel plate capacitor is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["increase its capacitance","decrease its capacitance","insulate the plates from each other","increase the magnetic field between plates"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A substance has a half life of 5mins. After 6mins, the count rate was observed to be 400. What was its count rate at zero time<\/strong><\/p>","options":["200","1200","1600","2400"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>If light with proton energy 2ev is incident on the surface of a metal with work function 3ev. Then<\/strong><\/p>","options":["no electron will be emitted","the few electrons emitted will have maximum kinetic energy of 1ev","the few electrons emitted will have a maximum kinetic energy of 3ev","many electrons will be emitted with maximum kinetic energy of 5ev"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a nuclear fusion experiment, the loss of mass amounts to 1.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>g. The amount of energy obtained from the fusion (speed of light 3.0 x 10<sup>3<\/sup> ms<sup>-1<\/sup>) is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["3.0 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","5.0 x 10<sup>-1<\/sup>J","9.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>J","9.0 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"}]